{
  "reference_number": "9378",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Preferably two, but pragmatically only if needed - three, with careful safeguards, aware that historically these have been at times a\n sham which has also depressed the value of national carbon units."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Ideally we should have an absolute target."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "There needs to be a strong cooperative model between national government and local authorities. This is especially important in the\n\narea of transport which is one of the leading causes of carbon emissions. National and local government need a coordinated and\nfiscal response to transport needs including commitment to cycleways, walkways, public transport and electric vehicles and their\n\nservicing as well as less reliance on transport using carbon based fuels. In addition there needs to be a unified approach to creating\nvibrant city centres which support the arts, sport and community involvement. This will have impacts on reducing the need for wider\n\ntravel including to overseas destinations, plane travel being another huge contributor to carbon emissions. The above changes have\nspin off effects on improved health and well being with such things as an increase in exercise, social connection and well being and a\nreduction in obesity rates. There also needs to be collaboration with other ministries such as the Ministry for Primary Industries and\n\nMinistry of Health. There will be wide reaching effects on all levels of NZ society such as an increase in diseases spread by\nmosquitoes, and collaboration and information sharing will help to plan for and mitigate some of these consequences. Community\n\ngroups also need to be consulted including, but not restricted to, farmers, iwi, forestry owners, the business community, schools, AA\netc"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But I would put business competitiveness on the essential list, and also an understanding of social policy for example social capital,\n\nhappiness quotas."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The elephant in the room is the farming industry which in NZ contributes 60% to our greenhouse gas emissions and currently is not\nincluded in the ETS. Obviously farming is an important cornerstone to our economy so any change needs to be done in a respectful\n\nand mindful way. Options could include a commitment, in collaboration with the MOH, encouraging vegetable based diets with the\ninherent spin-off effects of improved health such as a reduction in heart disease and bowel cancer. Also there could be commitment\n\nto funding R&D into less methane-producing feed for stock and for genetic selection for less gas producing breeds. Another option\nis proactive support for changing land use such as converting farms to horticulture or forestry. This could have further benefits on\nwater and air quality, especially tree planting on waterways."
    }
  ]
}
